Guide to the Paul Rotha Correspondence,
Rare Book and Manuscript Library Columbia University Libraries
Paul Rotha Correspondence,
1930-1953
Rotha, Paul, 1907-1984.
32 items (1 box)
Columbia University. Rare Book and Manuscript Library, New York, NY.
4079284
Biographical Note
Film director, producer, author of works on the history of films, journalist, pioneer in documentary films.
Scope and Content
A series of letters from Rotha to his wife, containing personal and professional observations during his early career in England and in New York. Also, one letter from Rotha to Peter Hunt.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged into 1 series:
Series I: Cataloged Correspondence
Subjects
Hunt, Peter.; Documentary films.; Motion picture industry--England.; Motion picture industry--New York (State)--New York.; Motion picture producers and directors.; Authors.; Journalists.
Access Restrictions
This collection has no restrictions.
This collection is located on-site.
Acquisition
07/--/79 M-79-07 736556 Purchase
- Series I: Cataloged Correspondence
  The series is arranged in chronological order.
  - Subseries I.1: 1930
    The 1930 letters were written when Rotha was in London finishing up the publication of The Film Till Now, organizing a film group, writing articles for film magazines, and seeking work in film.
    - Rotha, Paul To Louise Lee Rotha (Mrs. Paul), [1930?], (2 p. a.l.s.) (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Rotha, Paul To Louise Lee Rotha (Mrs. Paul), [1930], (1 p. a.l.) (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Rotha, Paul To Louise Lee Rotha (Mrs. Paul), [1930], (2 p. a.l.) (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Rotha, Paul To Louise Lee Rotha (Mrs. Paul), [1930], (4 p. a.l.) (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Rotha, Paul To Louise Lee Rotha (Mrs. Paul), 1930, (2 p. a.l.) (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Rotha, Paul To Louise Lee Rotha (Mrs. Paul), [1930?], (2 p. a.l.s.) (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Rotha, Paul To Louise Lee Rotha (Mrs. Paul), 1930, (3 p. a.l.) (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Rotha, Paul To Louise Lee Rotha (Mrs. Paul), 2 May 1930, (2 p. a.l. (with envelope) (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Rotha, Paul To Louise Lee Rotha (Mrs. Paul), [1930?], (2 p. a.l.s.) (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Rotha, Paul To Louise Lee Rotha (Mrs. Paul), [1930], (2 p. a.l.) (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Rotha, Paul To Louise Lee Rotha (Mrs. Paul), 15 May 1930, (4 p. a.l. (with envelope) (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Rotha, Paul To Louise Lee Rotha (Mrs. Paul), 20 May 1930, (4 p. a.l. (with envelope) (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Rotha, Paul To Louise Lee Rotha (Mrs. Paul), 22 May 1930, (2 p. a.l. (with envelope) (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Rotha, Paul To Louise Lee Rotha (Mrs. Paul), 30 May 1930, (2 p. a.l.s. (with envelope) (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Rotha, Paul To Louise Lee Rotha (Mrs. Paul), 12 June 1930, (2 p. a.l. (with envelope) (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Subseries I.2: 1932-1934
    During this period, Rotha was writing articles for Film Quarterly and making documentaries for British Instructional Films. The letters mention work on the films Contact, Rising Tide, and Shipyard. They also mention the encouragement Rotha received from John Grierson and others.
    - Rotha, Paul To Louise Lee Rotha (Mrs. Paul), [1932?], (4 p. a.l.s.) (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Rotha, Paul To Louise Lee Rotha (Mrs. Paul), [1932], (1 p. a.l.) (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Rotha, Paul To Louise Lee Rotha (Mrs. Paul), 11 May 1933, (2 p. a.l.s. (with envelope) (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Rotha, Paul To Louise Lee Rotha (Mrs. Paul), 26 May 1933, (1 p. a.l. (with envelope) (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Rotha, Paul To Louise Lee Rotha (Mrs. Paul), 29 May 1933, (1 p. a.l. (with envelope) (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Rotha, Paul To Louise Lee Rotha (Mrs. Paul), [1934], (2 p. a.l.) (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Rotha, Paul To Louise Lee Rotha (Mrs. Paul), [1934], (3 p. a.l.s.) (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Rotha, Paul To Louise Lee Rotha (Mrs. Paul), [1934], (2 p. a.l.s.) (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Rotha, Paul To Louise Lee Rotha (Mrs. Paul), [1934?], (2 p. a.l.s.) (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Subseries I.3: 1937
    In 1937, Rotha received a Rockefeller Foundation Grant to promote British Film through the Museum of Modern Art Film Library. In his letters to his wife, he describes his reactions to New York and to the people he meets there.
    - Rotha, Paul To Louise Lee Rotha (Mrs. Paul), September 1937, (2 p. a.l.s. (with envelope) (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Rotha, Paul To Louise Lee Rotha (Mrs. Paul), 30 September 1937, (3 p. t.l.s. (with envelope) (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Rotha, Paul To Louise Lee Rotha (Mrs. Paul), 5 October 1937, (3 p. t.l.s. (with envelope) (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Subseries I.4: 1938-1939
    After Rotha returned from America, John Grierson offered him a staff position with his documentary consultant firm, Film Centre Ltd. The following letters appear to have been written in 1939 when Rotha was directing The Times. Preproduction for the The Times was through Film Centre while Realist Film Unit handled production.
    - Rotha, Paul To Louise Lee Rotha (Mrs. Paul), [1938], (1 p. a.l.s.) (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Rotha, Paul To Louise Lee Rotha (Mrs. Paul), [1939?], (1 p. a.l.s ) (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Rotha, Paul To Louise Lee Rotha (Mrs. Paul), [1939], (1 p. t.l.s.) (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Rotha, Paul To Louise Lee Rotha (Mrs. Paul), [1939], (1 p. t.l.s.) (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Subseries I.5: 1953
    Rotha was head of documentary film department for the British Broadcasting Corporation (BBC) from 1953 to 1955. This memo is a gift of Winifred A. Myers, 1980.
    - Rotha, Paul To Peter Hunt, 16 November 1953, (1 p. t.l.s. (memorandum) (Box 1, Folder 5)